<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon against murder: by occasion of the Romanists putting the Protestants to death in the dukedome of Savoy. / By William Towers, B.D.</title>
            <author>Towers, William, 1617?-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94768</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1962</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E835_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207410</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866462</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866462</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168138</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94768)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168138)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 127:E835[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon against murder: by occasion of the Romanists putting the Protestants to death in the dukedome of Savoy. / By William Towers, B.D.</title>
                  <author>Towers, William, 1617?-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Mosely, at the Princes Armes, in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 5.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Exodus XX, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168138:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON AGAINST MURDER: By occaſion of the ROMANISTS putting the PROTESTANTS to death in the Dukedome of SAVOY.</p>
            <p>BY WILLIAM TOWERS, B.D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cyprian. Ep. 6. Martyribus, &amp; Confiſſoribus.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>O Beatam Eccleſiam noſtram, quam ſic Honor Divinae Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationis Illuminat! quam <hi>Temporibus noſtris,</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſus Martyrum ſanguis illuſtrat!</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſely,</hi> at the Princes Armes in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:168138:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168138:2"/>
            <head>TO The Perſons both of ſecular Quality, and of ſolid Piety, in the beliefe and Practice of Gods true Religion in his Church truly Reformed, Sir HUMPHREY TRACY, <hi>Baronet.</hi> and his excellent Lady.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et it, I beſeech you, be eſteemed no fault, that I do, what God has done, Joyn you together; that I do it in this Dedication, I have much of reaſon for it; This was the laſt Sermon preacht in your Church, before I finally underſtood, that after all the endeavours of you both, and my own frequent atteudance upon others, I may not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Countrey leave to be a conſtant preacher there: and what ſhould I after doe, but make my publick acknowledgments to you both, for your hearty and coſtly endeavours? and let my hinderers know that though they have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judic't
<pb facs="tcp:168138:3"/>me, in my beſt deſires, of ſerving thoſe whom I much deſir'd to ſerve, becauſe of their mutual deſires that I ſhould do it, in my great hopes, of making Gods ſervice to proſper un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch Religious Patronage, whoſe <hi>preſent lives</hi> would not only be notes upon my Sermons, but better Sermons then mine; and notes to me, out of which to make Sermons; that though I might take it unkindely, that a Proteſtant of England is deny'd (I know not why) by his fellow Proteſtants, a Son of the Church, by Sons of the ſame Church (for ſure neither they nor I are Romaniſts:) yet I do not, both becauſe they ahve teſtify'd to your worſhip, under their hands, that they have no exception againſt me, unleſſe a ſuſpicion that I differ in judgement, (and yet I know not theirs, nor they mine; or, if I do, have we not <hi>leave</hi> to differ? they from me, and I from them:) and becauſe they ſo kindly deny me, as if the Emolument were too ſmall for me; and yet is any thing ſmall, which is moſt intenſely aim'd at? <hi>qui ſic Amas (I</hi> am Gall'd, and pincht, and muſt wince and ſpeak) <hi>Quomodo Oſurus es?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next to my confeſſions to both your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and Acquittances to them all, and
<pb facs="tcp:168138:3"/>Gratitude to the great civility of one of them, I have more reaſons why I print on this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to deſire all, to joy with me, that Authority does (not only do it, but publiſh, and profeſſe to do it,) loath murther, and deteſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery; O, may it ever abound, with more and more Clemency at home and abroad, and ſhut out Romaniſme by the certain Rule of <hi>Orderly</hi> reformation!</p>
            <p>Secondly, to intreat all my miniſterial bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to joyn their forces of Tongue and pen, and prayer, againſt the Common enemy to all the Reformed Churches; that we would not make way for them <hi>Diſſidiis noſtris Vires ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as augendi;</hi> that we would be wiſely ſuſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that the preſent many-headed differences amongſt us, are contrived, and rais'd, and fomented, by the Adverſarie of us all, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen many Gates, at which the one Head with three Crowns upon it, to enter; this Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty has taught us to fear, requiring us cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably to do for them that ſuffer, and Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimouſly to <hi>ſuffer with them when God calls us to it;</hi> our own ſins, and the old arts
<pb facs="tcp:168138:4"/>and Ambuſhes, and frauds of Rome may teach us this fear; if that Authority would give me leave to beſeech, that differences at home, might be reconcil'd by the <hi>Standing Rule</hi> (at leaſt, in this way of neceſſity and dread) the Church of <hi>England</hi> would yet produce abler men againſt all her enemies, then ſhe (I am almoſt afraid to call her whore) who has made us enemies againſt our ſelves can produce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us: a ſtrong and <hi>Choſen</hi> man, when his augry and merry Paſſions were over, when he had ſomewhat more to doe with the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> ſeem'd to remember the end of another Verſe, that of <hi>Ovid: — Virtus, &amp; in hoſte, Probatur,</hi> when we acknowledg'd oue to be a very learned man, who I am confident, would bend all his force againſt <hi>Rome</hi> (I, and batter her too) did he not believe it conſcientiouſly neceſſary, to ſet himſelfe in the Gap, againſt ſome fallings out at home: And when, with all humble mrdeſty, I have beſeech Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, I may take leave to beſeech my own bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren one, <hi>in the Faith which was once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd,</hi> ſadly to conſider what the meaning of ſome new lights are; light ſhould be ſo cleare
<pb facs="tcp:168138:4"/>as to declare it ſelf; but ſome are ſtill in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Ignorance; they cannot tell what is the ground; and fountain, and firſt fire that kindles theſe lights; only they are wary e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſuſpect, that it is ſome <hi>Purgatory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire</hi> has done it; may it not be a Notion obtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from ſubtil Rome? and unawares ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd in the ſimplicity of ſome mens hearts? who when they are a while, injur'd in the matter of this expreſſion, and believe it to be <hi>the word of God in their Conſcience,</hi> may at length, be brought to interpret it by Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (that muſt not appear, too ſoon, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maturely, in it's own face) which ſome call the <hi>unwritten</hi> word of God? and yet <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and the word of God are, in Scripture, which is Gods word <hi>ſynonima,</hi> ſignificative of the ſame thing, and convertible; and then the <hi>unwritten word</hi> of ſome, what is it but a <hi>Romiſh Bull,</hi> the <hi>unwritten Scripture?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that my ſuſpecters may know, he whom they lay aſide loves the Errours of Rome as little as they do, (not Popiſhly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted at all) and would himſelf bring ſtraw, if their better abilities were at leaſure, to hew
<pb facs="tcp:168138:5"/>out ſtone, to make a wall againſt her.</p>
            <p>I muſt conclude, more particularly to both your worſhips, with my humble requeſts to you, to pardon my miſery, that I muſt not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy my <hi>own</hi> liberty, in ſerving <hi>you:</hi> and with my heartie prayers to God for you, that you may ſo exceptablie <hi>ſerve</hi> him <hi>here,</hi> as to <hi>Reign</hi> with him in Heaven.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Though not at</hi> Stanway, Your moſt Faithful Servant, every where elſe, <hi>WILLIAM TOWERS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168138:5"/>
            <head>A Sermon againſt Murder.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EXOD. 20.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt not Kill.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I have deſign'd to be brief upon the ten Commandements, not handling them now, <hi>Ex Inſtituto,</hi> as they are ſet down by <hi>Moſes,</hi> but <hi>Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim,</hi> in a more large acceptation of them, as they are <hi>all</hi> of them comprehended in thoſe <hi>few</hi> words of <hi>S. John, the Commandements of God.</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 5.2. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though for this reaſon, I ran through the four firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, in one Sermon, and made the fifth alone the entire Subject of an other, becauſe of the multiplicity of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in it; which yet I did not ſo much as <hi>ſummarily</hi> diſpatch, having ſpoken but half a word of the duty of <hi>Diſciples</hi> to their <hi>Teacher</hi> (my own intereſt compel'd me to ſpeak no more) and not half a ſyllable of the duty of the <hi>younger</hi> to the <hi>Aged,</hi> of the <hi>Inſtructed</hi> (any otherway) to the <hi>Couſellour,</hi> of the <hi>ſcholar</hi> (that peculiar way) to the <hi>Maſter;</hi> (want of time infoc't me not to ſpeak of theſe at at all) all of theſe, He that is the <hi>School-maſter.</hi> He that gives <hi>Counſel,</hi> and he that is the <hi>Aged man,</hi> being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended under the notion of <hi>Father,</hi> and a ſeveral reſpective <hi>Honour</hi> being due to the ſeveral kinds of <hi>Fatherhood</hi> in each of theſe; yet, at this time, I ſhall intirely inſiſt upon this one ſhort text, and large Command, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill; Providence</hi> having ſo order'd it, that this Prophibition is next to be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168138:6"/>ſpoken of, on this very day, on which <hi>Authority</hi> has appointed thoſe to be releiv'd by the collection of your liberality, who ſo miſerably ſuffer by the barbarous inhumane breach of this ſixth Commandement, in all the branches of it, as it relates to the very act of murther.</p>
            <p>All thoſe ſeveral branches I ſhall briefly enquire into, and make them the Diviſion of my Text, that when you have ſeen how <hi>diſobedient</hi> and Rebellious to <hi>God</hi> it is, to inflict all theſe degrees of ſufferings, how <hi>ſad,</hi> and greivous, how wretched, and almoſt inſupportable it is for <hi>man</hi> to endure them all, your hearts may be the more enlarged to ſupply their needs, and thereby to defend and maintain the lives of the ſurvivours.</p>
            <p>This alſo is part of this Command. Every <hi>Negative</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of God, has it's <hi>Poſitive</hi> duty incumbent upon man; not onely, <hi>thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> not take <hi>away</hi> life, That's the Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive part of this duty, and it is but part; but alſo, thou ſhalt as much as in thee lies, ſuccour and ſupport life; That's the poſitive, and both theſe are the whole.</p>
            <p>So many other Branches there are, which grow out of this root, <hi>thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> that I dare not ſo much as <hi>Name</hi> them <hi>before</hi> the Sermon, becauſe I can do no more <hi>then</hi> name them <hi>in</hi> the Sermon; you ſhall meet with them in their Order; Firſt and cheifly, of the root that beares them, <hi>thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> not take life away.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not do it, <hi>unworthily,</hi> illegally; that interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation muſt run through every part of the Text; Elſe, there will be no juſt power left, to take his life away, who wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully takes away another mans; elſe one Scripture will thwart another. How many Commands are there, in the Word of God to take life away, upon ſpecial and due occaſions! but then they are the Judges, Publick perſons, men in Authority, that may, that muſt do this; and when they do this, take life away, though they do <hi>Kill,</hi> yet they doe no murther, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſtill that they do it upon <hi>juſt and due</hi> occaſions; elſe, murther may, ſometimes, and unadviſedly, be Committed with the very ſword of Juſtice; and when they <hi>thus</hi> kill, they doe not ſo much take life away, as preſerve life; they kill the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168138:6"/>murtherer, that neither he, nor others, by his unpuniſht ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, may murther more; take away this ſword, and there is nothing elſe left but <hi>ſword;</hi> what ſhall we be without his protection, but <hi>ſpelunca latronum &amp; Homicidaram?</hi> what ſhall we do, and ſuffer, but Rob, and be Rob'd, Kill, and be Kill'd! The <hi>Officer</hi> may do this; but <hi>Thou ſhalt not Kill,</hi> thou the <hi>Private</hi> man muſt not do it; I will not ſo much as name (though many good men do it) a <hi>ſe defendendo,</hi> to tolerate this act of private-killing; both, leaſt this excuſe may be <hi>pretended</hi> where <hi>Really</hi> it is not, and beeauſe a better Chriſtian has well taught me that a good perfect Chriſtian,
<note place="margin">D. <hi>H. H.</hi> in his Practic. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> out of the abundance of Chriſt Commanded Charity, will rather <hi>Die</hi> then <hi>Kill;</hi> and, therefore, may the <hi>Officer</hi> do this, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breach of this Command; becauſe, elſewhere, He is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to do it; and, therefore too, muſt the <hi>unworthily,</hi> the <hi>illegally</hi> be interpreted of the Prohibition in this Text, thoſe many other plaine and evident Texts in Scripture giving light and luſtre thus to expound this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not Kill;</hi> the inhibition is plaine, againſt the murther of any private man in any Nation; and 'tis as plaine againſt one Nation Invading Another, to kill and Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre there; for, though it be a <hi>Pope,</hi> who is Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and, perhaps, <hi>ſupreme There in Cathedra non-Catholica,</hi> yet <hi>Rome</hi> is not <hi>Savoy;</hi> though it be a <hi>Duke,</hi> who, perhaps, is Prince and <hi>Cheife</hi> in <hi>Savoy,</hi> yet <hi>Savoy</hi> is not <hi>England;</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> has no more Power to Maſſacre <hi>There,</hi> or the <hi>Duke Here,</hi> then a <hi>Private</hi> man has power to do it, either here, or there; and that, becauſe, be he Pope, or be he Duke, as great as he is at <hi>Home,</hi> where he <hi>Raigns,</hi> yet out of his <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> he is but a <hi>Private</hi> man <hi>Abroade:</hi> nay, let me ſay it, neither <hi>Pope,</hi> nor <hi>Prince,</hi> can at all <hi>Travel</hi> out of their <hi>own</hi> Dominions; when they are once paſt their Bounds, the <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>Prince</hi> ſtay behinde, their <hi>Pompe</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> are left upon the ſhoare; and only the <hi>Man,</hi> in each of them, croſſes the Seas; and whenever they ſhall do ſo, God in his mercy preſerve us from their malice, that neither they may be ſo outragious, to Maſſacre any of the people of God in this Land, nor that any
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168138:7"/>the people of God in this land may ever he ſo beguil'd and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſotted with ſuperſtition, as to beleive they have any power and Right to do it, to break this Command of God, <hi>Thou,</hi> thou that haſt no title at all to this Nation, <hi>Thou ſhalt not Kill here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, any the greateſt Potentates, in any their own Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, have not any the leaſt power, (power I mean of <hi>Right,</hi> though they have of <hi>Force</hi>) to take away the life of any their meaneſt ſubject, unleſſe according to the law of that place; much leſſe upon their own meer <hi>Arbitrarineſſe,</hi> to <hi>ſlay</hi> ſome <hi>Thouſands</hi> upon the Spot, and to <hi>drive out</hi> other <hi>Thouſands</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the <hi>Mountaines;</hi> this is ſuch a ſpot, which they will never be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to wipe off from their bloody ſoules, whileſt they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue either to <hi>practice</hi> this with their hands, or to believe in their ſoules that they may practice this: Againſt all ſuch Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitancies, and irregular Illegal Cruelties, even of the <hi>Greateſt,</hi> this Text ſtands in full force, thou (thou, <hi>O mighty man, who boaſteſt thy ſelf in miſchief</hi>) ſhalt not Kill; not <hi>Thus,</hi> not <hi>thus unworthily</hi> Kill; <hi>what ailed ye, ye mighty men, that of late ye made the poor Proteſtants to flie? ye inferiour Souldiers, that ye drave them back? ye Great perſons, that ye skipped over them like Rams, and ye little ones, like lambs? Tremble, all of you, at the preſence of the Lord, at the preſence of this command of the God of Jacob, Thou ſhalt not kill;</hi> above all, do not break Gods Command for Gods own ſake; Tempt us not by any more of theſe ſavageneſſes to apply that propheſie of Chriſt to you, <hi>The time Commeth, that whoſo killeth you, will think that he doth God ſervice, Ioh.</hi> 16.2. 'Tis neceſſary that all Chriſts propheſies Come to paſſe, but woe to that man by whom they thus come; 'tis a Zeal indeed this, but, like their Ignorant obedience, a Blinde one, Firſt, to put out their own eyes, and then the Eyes of the Proteſtants body, his Soule; 'tis that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone which ſees;
<note place="margin">Ariſtot.</note> 
               <hi>Oculus non videt, ſed videt Anima;</hi> open their eyes, O God, that they may no longer be the miſ-guided and dutiful ſons of deſtruction; that they who call themſelves by the name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſuites.</note> may learn ſome of his <hi>Meekneſſe,</hi> to ſuffer rather then to put to death; that they would endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168138:7"/>to plant Religion only as Chriſt did, with perſwaſion, and not with blood, unleſſe of his own true Diſciples, not of thoſe who oppos'd his Doctrine, that they would, as Chriſt <hi>ever</hi> did, <hi>Teach only openly,</hi> and not <hi>Creep into houſes, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſilly ones Captive</hi> (but, alas, then, the diſſemination of their Errours would be prevented) that they would, as Chriſt did, ſay plainly, <hi>It is I,</hi> and not put off their own name, and put on another, not put off the Prieſts Coat, and put on the ſouldiers, not pretend one falſe Religion, that they may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce another falſe Religion, and eſpecially, not to ſowe that Religion in the foule blood, as they take it to be, of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks as they call them; Still to this purpoſe, may I not aske of them, Is it enough whereby to Kill, becauſe he, I know not who, commands them to do it, that has no Scripture Authority to command it, unleſſe ſuch words as theſe, of that uſurper, whom God was offended at, <hi>Marke, and when I ſay ſmite, then Kill; fear not, have not I commanded you?</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.28. and is it not enough to refrain them from killing, by the clear words of that God whom we know, and whom they ſay, they know? <hi>thou ſhalt not kill.</hi> Will they upon this ſcore, <hi>take gifts to ſhed blood, Ezeck.</hi> 22.12. ſmite, and kill, for <hi>Pay,</hi> and under <hi>Command?</hi> will there, becauſe of this, be a <hi>Conſpiracy amongſt their very Prophets, divining lyes,</hi> unto <hi>them?</hi> will they, becauſe of <hi>Treaſure, and precious things,</hi> ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their Appetites <hi>to devoure ſoules?</hi> and their ſwords, to <hi>make many widowes? verſe</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>I am loth to tell them of the Ignorant folly of one of their ſide, who would needs finde expreſſe Text, wherewith to kill any Heretick, and therefore made uſe of that of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus, ch.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 10. Him that is an Heretick, <hi>de vita,</hi> reject; <hi>fuge</hi> ſaies another tranſlation, <hi>flie from him;</hi> but he, poor ſoul, would not flie from him, but rather out of his blinde Zeal to the Roman Hereſie, Firſt, cut the verbe in two peices, <hi>De vita,</hi> and then flie upon him, and cut the very throat of him; 'tis true, the word of God is a <hi>two-edged</hi> ſword; but this word of his, thus inexpertly weilded, is too <hi>Blunt</hi> a weapon, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to draw blood from any; had he proſper'd in this, what
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168138:8"/>ſtrange ſhift, by ſome ſuch like wilde adventure, would he have been put unto, to prove a Proteſtant to be an Heretick! and truly, his after-friends, though they have better Latine, have no better Religion, wherewith to wound us.</p>
            <p>By this time it appeares, if <hi>Great</hi> ones, without their own precincts, or within them, have no priviledge, Papal or Dukal, no Prerogative Royal, to ſet themſelves above the commands of that greater God who is <hi>higher then they,</hi> much more does this Text lay an <hi>Incruental</hi> obligation, a <hi>bond of peace</hi> upon all <hi>ſubject people,</hi> upon all private perſons, in their Townes, and Nations, and Travels.</p>
            <p>To every of <hi>you</hi> it is ſaid, on a more palpable eviction, <hi>thou ſhalt not kill;</hi> and well it is ſaid ſo; for, God ſaid it, and providentially is it ſaid ſo; for, the merciful God ſaid it; ſaid; no more then this, <hi>thou ſhalt not kill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In favour to Meak capacities, (and many ſuch there are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Vulgar Subjects) it is not ſaid, thou ſhalt not kill thy <hi>Brother,</hi> leſt they might be miſperſwaded of the lawfulneſſe to kill an <hi>Egyptian, quà</hi> ſuch; to ſlay him that is of a <hi>different</hi> perſwaſion, of a Religion <hi>thwarting</hi> theirs, as not being a <hi>Brother</hi> to them in the ſame <hi>Faith of Chriſt:</hi> let Rome be as ſeduc'd, as ſhe is willing to be, I would rather, were it poſſible, a <hi>Papiſt</hi> ſhould take away a <hi>hundred</hi> lives from me, all but (what is impoſſible) the <hi>life eternal,</hi> then that I ſhould take away his <hi>one</hi> life from him, upon that <hi>ſhadow</hi> of reaſon (for, it is too <hi>dark</hi> to <hi>appear</hi> to be reaſon) becauſe he is a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> what if he misbelieves he may do this to me? ſhall I, who diſprove, and condemn his misbeleif, misbelieve with him? no; I am ſuſtain'd againſt the miſcheif, by <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that ſeduction by <hi>Vindictamihi, avenge not your ſelves; for it is written, Vengeance is mine, I will repay, ſaith the Lord, Rom.</hi> 12.19. And yet, had it been written, in this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Text, thou ſhalt not kill thy <hi>Brother, S. Auſtin</hi> would ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, have told thee the due extent of this command he would have given thee to underſtand, that not only the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt,</hi> but the very <hi>Turke</hi> is thy <hi>Brother</hi> (and if ſo, a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> ſure, is a <hi>Brother</hi> to the Romaniſt, and ſhould not be, as ſome
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168138:8"/>of them would make him, only a <hi>Brother</hi> in <hi>bloody</hi> when he ſaies, that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> are the <hi>Parents</hi> of us <hi>all,</hi> and we all, in them, are <hi>Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not ſaid, Thou ſhalt not kill thy <hi>Neighbour,</hi> leſt ſome ſhallow conceptions, ſhould thence extort a bloody doctrine, that they might, <hi>Deo non obſtante,</hi> nay, perhaps further yet, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with Gods own leave, ſlay a <hi>Forrainer;</hi> And yet, the ſame <hi>S. Auſtm,</hi> who is <hi>ſibi conſtans,</hi> will, elſewhere, tell thee, <hi>Homo Homini proximus,</hi> that every one man is neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to every other man, and therefore no one man may ſlay another; nay, the Text of Chriſt will tell you as much; <hi>which thinkeſt thou of theſe three was neighbour to him that fell among thieves? Luke</hi> 10 36. and he, who thus fell, he, to whom one of the three ſhew'd himſelf a neighbour, and the other two ſhould have done <hi>likewiſe v.</hi> 37. by what other name is he no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify'd and Characteriz'd, but by that of <hi>man,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Certain man went, and fell, v.</hi> 30. ſo certain it is, that he who is a man, is a <hi>neighbour</hi> (he and ſhe too, for, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is of both Genders) and neither of them may be ſlaine.</p>
            <p>Nay, 'tis not ſaid, thou ſhalt not kill thy <hi>enemy</hi> (thy enemy) leſt ſome deſperate zelot might thereupon undertake to kill <hi>Gods,</hi> though he ſpar'd his <hi>own</hi> enemy; and yet does not <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſay, <hi>Do not I hate them, O Lord, that hate thee? and am not I grieved with thoſe, that riſe up againſt thee? I hate them with a perfect hatred, I count th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m mine enemies. Pſa.</hi> 139.21.22. the enemies of God, are to be eſteem'd the enemies of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of God too; not only <hi>the Haters of God,</hi> but the very lovers of God, <hi>ſhall be found liars,</hi> if they eſteem them other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; and yet, in neither of theſe capacities, as haters of God, or, as enemies of the people of God, do they make a forfeiture of their lives: would you know then, how you may hate ſuch enemies? <hi>David</hi> has intimated to you how; it muſt be with a <hi>perfect hatred;</hi> and what that perfect hatred is, you may learn out of that meekly pious ancient Father, and Martyr, <hi>Ignatius ep. ad Philadelph.</hi> By his counſel, if you follow it, the <hi>Lord will deliver you from blood-guiltineſſe,</hi> or, as it ſounds in the Hebrew, and as <hi>Doway</hi> her ſelf tranſlates it, from <hi>Bloods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">With <hi>Doway,</hi> Pſ. 50. v. 16.</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:168138:9"/>from the maſſacring of many, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, you muſt indeed hate them who hate God; but then, he will preſently bound your hatred, the <hi>Remainder</hi> of your <hi>wrath</hi> he will reſtrain, he will tye up your hands behinde you, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, you muſt not ſo much as <hi>ſmite</hi> an <hi>enemy,</hi> though of Gods; if you do, you do it with the <hi>fiſt of wickedneſſe, Iſ.</hi> 58.4. you muſt not <hi>perſecute</hi> him, ſo much as out of his <hi>eſtate,</hi> much leſſe may you <hi>ſmite</hi> away his very <hi>life</hi> from him, and <hi>perſecute</hi> his body out of his skin, or his <hi>ſoul</hi> out of his <hi>body,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>enemies</hi> you may ſtill account them, and ſeperate from them, from <hi>Communion</hi> with their <hi>ſins,</hi> but not with their <hi>perſons,</hi> not from adviſing them, if they are of your Acquaintance and Neighbourhood, not from <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> to them, if they are of your <hi>Pariſh;</hi> Incluſively even to this laſt purpoſe, does it follow in that grave Religious <hi>Father</hi> (if that word be not diſlik't by thoſe, who are unwilling to be <hi>Sons</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, you muſt Admoniſh them of their ill manners, and labour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, (to recall) them to Repentance. And did not this After-runner of Chriſt, learn this Demeanour, think you, from Chriſts fore-runner? <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt <hi>preacht Mat,</hi> 3.1. the ſubject of his Sermon was <hi>Repentance, v.</hi> 2. when the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees and Sadducees came to him,</hi> though he knew them to be what he call'd them, <hi>a Generation of Vipers, v.</hi> 7. yet he did not un-Church them for all that, he did not <hi>Excommunicate</hi> them from his <hi>Congregation,</hi> he renew'd his <hi>Sermon</hi> and <hi>preacht</hi> even to <hi>them</hi> alſo, on the ſame ſubject; <hi>he ſaid unto them</hi> (and yet, <hi>not he,</hi> but the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> in him, an example high enough to follow) <hi>bring forth therefore fruits meet for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, v.</hi> 8. I will not now aske, Are thoſe, who are ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from, more <hi>Hypocritical</hi> then the <hi>Phariſees?</hi> do not others more loudly pretend to <hi>Holyneſse</hi> then they? are thoſe, who are <hi>ſeparated from,</hi> more <hi>Heretical</hi> then the <hi>Sadducees?</hi> do not others more boldly <hi>deny the Reſurrection</hi> then they? this I wil not aske; I will but give this reaſon for my ſhort digreſſion in theſe very few words; it is, what I may, if it be poſſible, as God
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168138:9"/>ſhall enable me; (and if he enable me, poſſible it is: His bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſpirit can work with <hi>five words</hi> utter'd with <hi>underſtanding</hi> and Charity as powerfully, as with a Folio) it is, that I may, by any meanes, <hi>ſave ſome,</hi> by reducing them from the Errour of their way.</p>
            <p>And is not all this inſtead of Stabbing him to the heart, a nobler, a worthier, a more generous, a more Chriſtian car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage towards an enemy? is not this the <hi>Perfection</hi> of <hi>Hatred?</hi> nay, is not this the perfection of that love, which Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf enjoyns towards enemies, <hi>Love them, Bleſse them, Do good to them, Pray for them, Mat.</hi> 5.44. ſuch a <hi>perfect hatred,</hi> ſuch a <hi>perfect love,</hi> which will <hi>Caſt out all fear</hi> from the <hi>man</hi> we <hi>thus</hi> love, from the <hi>enemy</hi> we <hi>thus</hi> hate?</p>
            <p>Hence, it eaſily appears, that though it had been ſaid, thou ſhalt not kill thy <hi>Brother,</hi> thy <hi>Neighbour,</hi> thy <hi>Enemy,</hi> no private man of what Nation or language ſoever has any excuſe whereby to palliate his ſpleen of killing another <hi>Private man,</hi> much leſſe of aſſaſſinating a <hi>Publick</hi> perſon; and that too, becauſe of the immediate ſubnexion of <hi>this</hi> command, to that of <hi>Honouring thy father,</hi> (which if it be not the very next here in <hi>Exodus,</hi> as ſome contend, who follow the <hi>Greek</hi> coppies, which place the Commandement concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Adultery</hi> betwixt that of <hi>Parents,</hi> and <hi>murther,</hi> yet thoſe very <hi>Greek</hi> coppies, in the book of <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> place that Commandement which forbids <hi>murther,</hi> before that which forbids <hi>Adultery;</hi> as alſo the <hi>Hebrew</hi> in <hi>both</hi> thoſe books) and hence, it much more appears, that this may not be done by any <hi>Private</hi> man, becauſe the Prohibition is Abſolute, unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, nothing elſe but Thou ſhalt not Kill. We have ſeen the extent and latitude of this killing, how <hi>univerſally</hi> it is forbid; ſee we next the heynouſneſſe of the guilt, the ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this ſin of committing murther.</p>
            <p>Though it might be enough, to teſtifie the iniquity of it, that, not to do it, is a <hi>moral</hi> law, written in the very heart of man, by the finger of God himſelf; that it is forbiddn even by Nature, and that, to every one man in the behalf of every o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man; ſo that, indeed, he who is but <hi>Compos mentis,</hi> who
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168138:10"/>has reaſon enough, not only <hi>in Radice,</hi> by a candid Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to denominate him, but, <hi>in Fructu,</hi> exerted reaſon, to evidence and demonſtrate him to be a man, cannot chooſe but know it: yet, to how much higher pitch and degree is this tranſgreſſion inhanc't and elevated, in that this command, which was before a command of God, is once again a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his, written by himſelf, in a Table of Stone!</p>
            <p>This indeed is too much the fault of <hi>worldly-wiſe</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, to meaſure <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad,</hi> either by their own <hi>warineſſe</hi> or <hi>indiſcretion,</hi> and not to impute it to the <hi>Performance</hi> or <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> of the command of God, either poſitive or Negative; he who kills a man, becauſe he ſhall not be <hi>known</hi> to have done it, or becauſe he knows, that he ſhall eſcape when he has done it, breaks the command of God twice over; Firſt, in killing, to ſatisfie his own rage, and then in deſpiſing the command of God, becauſe of his preſent ſecurity; this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prints the <hi>deepeſt ſtigma,</hi> 'tis a mark with the <hi>blackeſt coale</hi> upon the helliſh murtherer, that he ſets the <hi>Command of God at nought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See we yet more of the <hi>ſinfulneſſe</hi> of this man-<hi>ſlaying,</hi> 'tis abominable before God, and it is odious to man: <hi>Philo</hi> does ſo abhorre this ſin, that he is not content to call him that kills, a <hi>murtherous,</hi> unleſſe he call him a <hi>Sacrilegious</hi> perſon too, becauſe he puts to death that man who is the <hi>Image</hi> of God; 'tis not in this ſenſe ſaid by our Saviour, when he askt whoſe Image the penny bore, <hi>Give unto Caeſar the things which are Caeſars, and unto God the things which are Gods,</hi> that thou ſhouldſt therefore ſend the ſoul of man, which is the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God, to the God of that ſoul, <hi>the father of ſpirits,</hi> from off the point of thy ſword.</p>
            <p>He ſins againſt humane <hi>Society,</hi> to which we are born (<hi>in Coetum geniti ſumus,</hi> ſaies <hi>Seneca</hi>) which ſociety cannot be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, whileſt the lives of Innocents are in danger.</p>
            <p>He ſins againſt the <hi>law</hi> of the land, who ſlaies though a <hi>Nocent</hi> perſon, that has deſerv'd to dye, becauſe he ſnatches into his own hand that power which is the right of the law, and ties it upon the hilt of his ſword.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:168138:10"/>
            <p>This, at large, may ſufficiently implead the murtherer of guilt, unleſſe (if it may not be accounted too curious a ſearch) we raiſe the guilt higher then all this, from the practiſe of thoſe female-murtherers, who <hi>deſtroy the un-born Infants</hi> which are yet in their womb; and thereby, what they can, kill bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoul too, (I fear, their own) by hindring them from the benefit of baptiſme, who themſelves will be more aſham'd of their ſpurious child, then their child ſhall be <hi>Aſham'd of the Croſſe of Chriſt;</hi> Such early murthers as theſe, ſtories tells us of, and Chronicles tell us of practiſes quite out as ſavage; that, when a <hi>Great-belly'd Martyr</hi> has been burnt for an <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick,</hi> and the childe at once leapt out of the mothers belly, and the Adverſaries fire, the childe was thruſt back with a ſpiteful ſpear into the flame that it might dye the <hi>ſecond death,</hi> becauſe it was <hi>Baptiz'd</hi> only <hi>with fire: Deus, poſthac, meliora.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is ſin upon ſin; and what excuſe, what cloak for any of theſe? what Apology can any red murtherer make for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? 'tis not enough, that when he dyes for killing, he ſhall perhaps, have a red name in the Callender: That, which a Philoſopher of the <hi>Garamants</hi> ſaid (like a <hi>Philoſopher</hi>) boldly enough to <hi>Alexander</hi> when he came to Conquer them, were there truth in it, would never bear him out, <hi>If thou couldſt by thy bloody Victories, enjoy their lives, whom thou killeſt, to prolong thy own, as thou doſt inherit their goods to augment thy Revenue,</hi> it were <hi>more</hi> tolerable, though <hi>not at all,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſtill <hi>wicked; Vivitur ex Rapto</hi> would be a ſin, were it to live another mans life, which himſelf might live; as well as to live by another mans Acres whileſt the owner ſtarves to death, and no pretence would make this pardonable, unleſſe the kind-heartedneſſe of that brother in the Poet, who could no longer live his own life. <hi>Vive meo, frater, tempore, vive tuo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mart.</note>
            </p>
            <p>We have ſeen the latitude of the Command, and the Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the diſobedience to it; ſee we yet more of the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſneſſe of murther, from the miſeries which it inflicts on man.</p>
            <p>It ſeperates two of the deareſt friends that ever were,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168138:11"/>two that part which the greateſt greif, that ever any did; ſoul and body; friends they are, and ſuch friends as are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver well alone; the very <hi>beatified</hi> ſoul whileſt it is in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> is ſenſible of the <hi>Incompleatneſs</hi> of her joy <hi>there,</hi> till the body <hi>Partakes</hi> with it; they were labourers together in the <hi>Vineyard</hi> of Chriſt, and the ſoul when ſhe is got up to the <hi>heaven</hi> of Chriſt, does almoſt ſuſpect her ſelf of guilty <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> even in that moſt <hi>unſinful place,</hi> becauſe ſhe alone <hi>Reapes</hi> all the <hi>Joy</hi> which her body <hi>Sowing in tears</hi> helpt her to climb up unto; though it was the ſoul that <hi>believed,</hi> yet, that <hi>un-lipt</hi> ſoul does now of <hi>herſelf</hi> confeſſe, that when ſhe was on earth, ſhe <hi>confeſſed with her mouth unto Salvation;</hi> and in <hi>Equity,</hi> as well as <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> ſhe longs to kiſſe that mouth, by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union to the body; though it was the ſoul that <hi>lov'd God</hi> and the <hi>Saints of God,</hi> yet, the ſoul worſhipt God with the <hi>Head, Breaſt, and Knees bow'd down; with the hands, eyes, and Heart lifted up and the ſoul miniſter'd to the Needs of the Saints with the hands of the body;</hi> upon theſe accounts <hi>Theodoret</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes, the ſoul in heaven does thus beſeech God, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>good God haſten a Reſurrection to my body, and let us not be ſeperated in the Crown who were together Militant in the warfar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The love of theſe is ſo inſeparable each to other, even when themſelves are ſeparated, each from other, that ſome will needs fancy this to be the reaſon, why the body of the murthered perſon bleeds afreſh when the murtherer draws nigh, becauſe the ſoul in hate to him, that divorc'd her, and in love to the body about which ſhe ſtill hovers, diſturbs the body, and ſtirs the blood to the betraying of the man.</p>
            <p>This, though it be pretended from <hi>Natural</hi> reaſon, yet becauſe I finde it in the writings of a learned perſon of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the <hi>Romiſh perſwaſion,</hi> who is yet alive (and long may he be ſo, not to draw any to the Errours of his, <hi>with how pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a minde ſoever,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Erras, ſed bono ammo; Erras Honeſta Mente. Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eca.</note> but himſelf again to return to the truth of our Church) and becauſe I ſuſpect, it may be a ſnary founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, upon which to erect another ſnare of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> I ſhall therefore indeavour modeſtly, to refute this opinion, and to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168138:11"/>ſubſtitute another <hi>to examination</hi> in the place thereof, by asking two queſtions.</p>
            <p>The one; Is not the departed ſoul <hi>immediately</hi> (for, what can ſtop the <hi>paſſages</hi> of a <hi>ſpirit,</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> or Hell? or (as ſome dream) in <hi>Purgatory?</hi> if in heaven, it there knows ſo much of the will of God, that it will not dare to offer a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entry into its body, before the general reſurrection; if in hell, it is there ſo ſenſible of its already torments, and ſo jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of more additional torments by ſuch a re-union, that it will never be ſo ſelf-malicious, as to deſire ſo troubleſome an Aſſociate; if in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> that alſo (if a place it be) is a place of Torments; and the force of the reaſon recurres.</p>
            <p>The other; may not the Devil himſelf, by the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God himſelf, be the inſtrument of <hi>Gods juſtice,</hi> though he only deſigns <hi>mans ruine,</hi> in cauſing the blood to break forth, to the diſcovery and execution of the murtherer? we know, by <hi>Gallows</hi>-Confeſſions, how falſe the Devil hath been in his promiſes to witches, and does he not leave them to the Gibbet, and diſcover other malefactors, and this very mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer, only with this bad purpoſe, that they may all die be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times and have <hi>no more ſpace to repent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I inſiſt upon becauſe it pretends a general truth, (though it failes in the particular Application) that the ſoul loves the body (whether in the body, or out of it) and this aggravates the crime of the killing man.</p>
            <p>The ſoul and body love more then any; and they are more grieved to part, then any; the <hi>Italian</hi> ſaies well,
<note place="margin">Malvezzi.</note> There muſt be a great grief in <hi>any</hi> death (much more in ſuch a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent unwilling death) in that a very great ſin is the cauſe of every death; and does not this make his crime the greater, who with ſo many, and ſharpe pangs of each, divides two ſuch loving friends.</p>
            <p>In doing this, he makes them utterly uncapable of all the benefits and pleaſures of this world; he robs them of the uſe of all their eſtates, they ſhall enjoy them no more; he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives them of the comfort of all their friends, they ſhall ſee them no more; he perhaps <hi>ſurpriſeth</hi> them out of this world
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168138:12"/>before they are prepar'd for the <hi>Next;</hi> ſuch ſhall never <hi>ſee God;</hi> and what Devil can do worſe to man, then ſuch a cruel <hi>Soul</hi>-murtherer as this.</p>
            <p>The time would fail me, if I ſhould ſpeak any more of this command, in this extreamity of it, as it <hi>touches life;</hi> or if I ſhould ſpeak any more then one word of the other Branches and degrees of it.</p>
            <p>As murther is forbid, ſo all that conduces to it is forbid, there is a murther of the <hi>tongue</hi> in <hi>curſing</hi> to death, and of the <hi>heart</hi> in <hi>wiſhing</hi> to death, as well as of the <hi>hand</hi> in <hi>putting</hi> to death; <hi>he that hateth his brother, is a murtherer,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.15. 'tis the heart that hates, the tongue that utters, and the hand that executes that hatred, ſo that one man may be three mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers at one time, when he murthers him whom he both reviles and deſpiſes.</p>
            <p>In every command of God, that which makes way to the very laſt breach of it, is equally forbid as that laſt breach it ſelf;
<note place="margin">Biſhop of Peterburgh.</note> give me leave to confirm this by a religiouſly ſubtle ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of a piouſly learned Prelate of our Church (who was twice a father to my ſelf, Natural, and Dioceſan) <hi>Eve</hi> in her ſtate of <hi>Innocency</hi> when her <hi>knowledge was perfect,</hi> knew this full well; ſhe tells Satan, (and ſhe could not tell a lye, before ſhe fell) <hi>God hath ſaid ye ſhall not touch the tree, Gen.</hi> 3.3. and yet God only ſaid <hi>Thou ſhalt not eat of it, Gen.</hi> 2.17. yet becauſe <hi>touching</hi> muſt go before <hi>eating</hi> as the <hi>Preparation</hi> to it, to <hi>touch</hi> was <hi>forbid</hi> by God when he forbad to eat. In this very caſe, that all the degrees which lead up to ſuch a breach are forbid, I have the Teſtimony of Chriſt himſelf; He firſt repeats the command, <hi>thou ſhalt not bill, Matt.</hi> 5.21. and then preſently expounds it, thou ſhalt not be <hi>Angry,</hi> not ſay <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha,</hi> not <hi>Fool</hi> unto thy Brother <hi>v.</hi> 22. By this Authority we muſt alſo exclude <hi>Surfeiting and Drunkeneſſe and Effeminacy,</hi> which fore-run Dropſies, and Conſumptions, and Deaths, which murther eſtates, and bodies, and ſouls; in a word, <hi>every ſin</hi> is the bane of mans ſpirit, and the Baniſher of <hi>Gods,</hi> and we muſt practiſe all the contrary vertues, live tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately to our ſelves, peaceably and Charitably with all men,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168138:12"/>defend as occaſion ſerves, the reputation, livelihood, life of our Neighbour: I preach it now, and we muſt all practiſe it anon, in our ſeveral contributions to thoſe poor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, who ſo much need to be ſuccour'd by us, againſt thoſe who ſtrive one way more to break this ſixth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, by <hi>ſtarving</hi> them to <hi>death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God by his wiſedome teach us, and by his grace help us, to avoid thoſe and all other ſins, to perform theſe and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertues, that we may be bleſſed here on Earth, in the Integrity of Conſcience, to our ſatisfaction, and bleſſed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in heaven, in the viſion of God, to our admiration; and that for his ſake upon whoſe moſt precious body the Jewes broke this Commandement of God, even upon God himſelf; Jeſus Chriſt our ever living Lord, and only Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. To whom be glory, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
